Guide to the Joel Barlow Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Joel Barlow Collection
1780-1813
YCAL MSS 568
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.54
(6 boxes)
Barlow, Joel, 1754-1812
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources. For more information see catalog cards filed in the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Barlow, Joel (1754-1812), American businessman, diplomat, and poet.
Scope and Contents
The collection provides evidence of the personal and professional life of Joel Barlow between 1780 and 1813. Most notably the collection contains Barlow's continuing work on his epic poem The Vision of Columbus (1787), which he ultimately expanded and republished as The Columbiad (1807). The collection contains a printed version of The Vision of Columbus (Paris, 1793) with revisions and additional material, such as a list of subjects for illustration, estimates of printing costs, and preface. A letter to Barlow from Robert Fulton concerning copies The Columbiad found in a publisher's warehouse can be found in the correspondence series. The collection also includes autograph manuscript writings such as a chapter on "Means of Subsistence" from a larger work and a speech in response to the Republicans of Connecticut given at a political dinner.
In addition to documenting Barlow's writing career the papers also reflect his diplomatic service and business ventures. For example, in a letter to his wife Ruth Baldwin Barlow, Barlow discusses his experience as minister to Algiers. Several documents reflect Barlow's business interests, including a document composed while Barlow was serving as the European representative for the Scioto Associates. Barlow's increasing wealth can be seen in an indenture detailing the contents of his Washington, D.C. estate, Kalorama, created when Barlow leased his home to M. Serrurier, French minister to the U.S.
The collection contains several autograph letters written by Joel Barlow to his wife Ruth Baldwin Barlow, friends, and colleagues. Barlow corresponded with a number of notable people, including Sylvanus Bourne, Robert Fulton, Benjamin Latrobe, Fulwar Skipwith, and Noah Webster, among others.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1780-1813. II. Writings, 1793-1811. III. Business Papers, 1790-1811.
American literature -- 18th century; Authors, American -- 18th century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 18th century; Authors -- Connecticut -- 18th century; Diplomats -- United States -- 18th century; Poets -- Connecticut -- 18th century; Barlow, Joel, 1754-1812; Barlow, Joel, 1754-1812 ( Vision of Columbus); Barlow, Ruth, 1755-1818; Maret, Hugues-Bernard, duc de Bassano, 1763-1839
- Correspondence, 1780-1813; Series I; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains letters from Barlow to his wife Ruth Baldwin Barlow in addition to friends and colleagues. All letters are outgoing unless otherwise noted. The series also includes two third party letters, from Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de Lafayette, to Clara Baldwin, and from Presley Neville to Jonathan Russel (enclosed with Neville's letter to Barlow).
  - Babcock, Elisha, autograph letter, signed, Washington, 1805 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Removed from Columbiad, Paris, 1813. Letter includes poem for use as Post-boy's New Year's address to readers of the American Mercury, Hartford.
  - Barlow, Ruth Baldwin, autograph letter, signed, draft, Algiers, Algeria, 1796 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Docketed in Barlow's hand: Copy / to Mrs. B.
  - Barlow, Ruth Baldwin, 3 autograph letters, signed, to Joel Barlow, Hartford, Connecticut and Paris, France, 1782 February 13 - 1812 November 15-16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bishop, Abraham, autograph letter, signed, Kalorama, Washington, 1808 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bourne, Sylvanus, 3 letters, signed, Paris, France, 1811 September 21 - 1812 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Each of the letters is in the hand of a different amanuensis and signed by Barlow.
  - Bradley, Stephen R., autograph letter, signed, Paris, France, 1812 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clarke, Jabez, autograph letter, signed, Windham, Connecticut, 1788 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cutts, Richard, autograph letter, signed, Paris, France, 1811 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Concerns watch that Congressman Cutts commissioned Barlow to buy.
  - Dearborn, Honorable Henry, autograph letter, signed, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1807 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fulton, Robert, autograph letter, signed, Kalorama, Washington, 1811 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fulton, Robert, autograph note to Joel Barlow, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, concerning copies of Barlow's Columbiad found in the publisher's warehouse., 1812 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hopkins, Samuel M., autograph letter, signed, Paris, France, 1798 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Latrobe, Benjamin, Paris, France, 1812 February 29 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lee, William, autograph letter, signed, London, England, 1805 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Meigs, Josiah, autograph letter, signed, Kalorama, Washington, 1809 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, to Clara Baldwin, autograph letter, signed, 1813 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, to Ruth Baldwin Barlow, 1813 September 1
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Stored in: Oversize box 5
  - Maret, Hugues-Bernard, duc de Bassano, 65 letters to Joel Barlow, Paris, France, 1811 October 21 - 1813 January 11 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    In French; written as Napoleon's Minister of foreign affairs to Barlow as American ambassador to Paris. The letters are docketed with notes of their content, and three are accompanied with contemporary manuscript translation into English.
  - Madison, Dolly, autograph letter, signed, from Ruth Baldwin Barlow, New York, 1813 December 16
  - National Institute of France, autograph letter, signed, copy, Kalorama, Washington, 1808 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Presenting a copy of his Columbiad, with, on verso, Barlow's copy of the reply of the Institute (Joachim Le Breton, perpetual secretary), Paris, France, October 15, 1808.
  - Neville, Presley, autograph letter, signed, to Barlow, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, docketed in Barlow's hand, 1811 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes autograph letter, signed, from Presley Neville to Jonathan Russell, care of Barlow, dated June 7, 1811.
  - Phillips, Richard, autograph letter, signed, Kalorama, Washington, 1809 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Skipwith, Fulwar, letter from Ruth Baldwin Barlow, Paris, France, 1799 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Skipwith, Fulwar, 4 autograph letters, signed, Paris, France, 1801 July 10 - 1804 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Watson, James, 3 autograph letters, signed, London, England, and Paris, France, 1792 February 13 - 1793 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Webster, Noah, 3 autograph letters, signed, Hartford, Connecticut, 1780 January 19 - 1786 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Writings, 1793-1811; Series II; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Series II is organized alphabetically.
  The series contains autograph manuscripts by Barlow as well as heavily annotated printed versions of his The Vision of Columbus.
  - The Columbiad: A Poem
    - Early version, printed version (Paris: Printed at The English Press, 1793), corrected. Consists of octavo printed pages with handwritten corrections, interleaved with quarto sheets bearing additional revisions, with occasional octavo and smaller leaves tipped or pasted in. Preliminary material includes list of subjects for illustration, estimates of cost of printing, and preface., After 1793 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      No Subnote Content
    - Intermediate version, printed version (Paris: Printed at The English Press, 1793), corrected, interleaved with quarto sheets bearing additional revisions. Preliminary material includes dedication, list of subjects for illustration, and preface. An index of names and a list of corrections appear at the end., After 1793 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Includes copy of The New England Quarterly with an article by Ezra K. Maxfield on the manuscript.
    - Final version, printed version (Paris: Printed at The English Press, 1793), corrected. Incorporates occasional octavo printed pages with smaller leaves tipped or pasted in. The notes and an index of names appear at the end., After 1793 (Box 3, Folder 26-33)
  - Lines Presented With a Rose To Miss Anica Preble, autograph manuscript, 1811 February (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Attributed to Joel Barlow.
  - Means of Subsistence, Chapter VI, autograph manuscript, corrected (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Consists of Barlow's definition of "a state of nature," the beginning of a chapter of a proposed work on political science.
  - Notes, autograph manuscript, chiefly on Barlow's reading, circa 1805-1806 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Response to an address from the Republicans of Connecticut, autograph manuscript, corrected, given at a dinner arranged by Abraham Bishop in Barlow's honor, 1805 October (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Business Papers, 1790-1811; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  The series consists of a number of business documents, including a document relating to the Scioto Associates, a consular certificate detailing goods being sent from France to the U.S., a financial document, and an indenture relating to Barlow's property Kalorama.
  - Autograph document, signed, a translation into English of a document in French executed by Barlow as agent and attorney of Manassah Culter, Winthrop Sargent, and William Duer, and F. M. J. de Barth and A. Coquet, purchasers of the lands of Scioto. With Barlow's certification of comparison with the original, Paris, France, 1790 July 23 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Consular certificate, executed by Stephen Cathalan, Jr., American vice-consul, with Barlow's handwritten declaration concerning his shipment of various goods from France to the United States, 1796 January 22 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Printed form of the Caisse d'escompte du commerce, Paris, for the payment of 3,000 francs, filled in and signed by Barlow. Tipped to the document is an unsigned manuscript note, relating to the payment of the order., 1801 September 6 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Indenture between Barlow and M. Serrurier, French minister to the U.S., leasing Kalorama for a period of three years, with inventory of furniture in the house., 1811 March 28 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, to Ruth Baldwin Barlow, 1813 September 1 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Madison, Dolly, autograph letter, signed, New York, 1813 December 16 (Box 5, Folder 43)